Right.
So far we have just changed the spawn speed to a variable for our obstacle car.
But as you know, our trees and foliage also have the same spawn in effect, so let's do the same for
them.
So moving over to this sprite, you can see that it is set to 0.6 to 0.3.
So our spawn speed is currently 0.6.
And we can simply drag this variable into here.
Then 0.3 is half of 0.6.
Instead of timesing it by two, like with our car.
We can divide it by two.
So grabbing this divide from the operators, sticking in our variable and typing in two.
And quickly hitting play once again.
Nothing new happens yet, but as you can see, it works.
So now that our spawning speed has been switched from hard coded values to variables, the next thing
we need to change is our movement speed.
Now in our code we have three different sprites that move down.
We have our obstacle sprite, our tree sprite, and our road lane sprite.
So firstly with our road sprite.
As you can see, our movement is determined by this change y by negative ten value.
So let's simply grab our movement speed variable, drag it into here.
Then let's quickly set our movement speed variable to minus ten and double click.
Then if we hit play, as you can see that works perfectly.
Next.
Moving over to our tree and foliage sprite.
Here you can see we also have movements set to a hard coded minus ten value.
So quite simply we can just replace this hard coded value with this variable.
And that's it.
So finally we can move over to our obstacle car.
Here, as you can see, we set this value to minus five instead of minus ten.
And we did this because we wanted our car to move just a bit slower than our road, which gave it the
illusion that it's moving forward.
So once again, we can swap out the static value with our movement speed variable.
But to make sure that it moves at a slower speed than our road and trees, we can grab a plus operator,
stick it in here and enter in five.
And since minus ten plus five equals minus five, we get back to the same value we had before.
So finally clicking play, we can test out if everything is working.
And yep, our game is running as it was before.
However, our code is now super robust and adaptable.
So time to move on to the fun part.
So we put in a lot of work restructuring our code, but our game basically plays the same as how we
had it.
So let's look at how we can make use of this new and improved code by adding levels to our game.
But before we change anything, let's first create a new sprite.
Now it really doesn't matter which sprite you select here, and you will see why in a second.
But after you have selected the sprite, we can also go into the costume editor.
Select the entire object and hit backspace and you probably really confused now.
But basically what we're going to do is use the sprite to set all our variables in our game.
Now, why this is nice is because we have one space where all our variables are set, and this makes
it easy to change values, upgrade, and make changes to our game.
And also it keeps us super organized.
Plus, who doesn't like to be organized?
Well, at least when it comes to programming.
So first things first, let's add in our most crucial block when start clicked.
Then moving down to our variables, let's drag in two of these set variable value blocks and how we
can set spawn speed and movement speed.
And what we want to do is just set it to the current value.
We have that now to ensure our game always starts at the speed.
So that's 0.6 and minus ten.
Now to increase the difficulty, all you need to do is grab a forever loop, a wait block, and then
two of these change variable by blocks.
So with that we can set our wait to eight seconds.
Then we can set this block to change spawn speed and the other to change movement speed.
So for our spawn speed variable, it is currently set to 0.6.
So we only want to make small adjustments here.
So what I'll do is change the spawn speed by -0.02.
This way our cars will slowly start spawning and faster.
Then for our movement speed we can change this value by minus one.
Now, before we hit play, let's quickly understand what is going on here.
So firstly our game is set to its initial level one speed.
Then every eight seconds we slowly decrease the amount of time it takes for our cars to spawn in.
And we also decrease our movement speed by minus one, which gets our cars and the obstacles to appear
like they are moving faster and faster as the game progresses.
Now.
This time, if we play the game, you will notice that every eight seconds these values decrease and
our game starts to get faster and faster.
Now, before we wrap up this lesson, let's quickly add a score element to this game.
You know, for bragging rights of course.
And to do this, all we need to do is create a new variable which we can call score.
Next we can add a set score to zero like we see with these variables.
Click the.
And finally, every eight seconds we can go ahead and change the score by, let's say, 43, because,
I mean, who doesn't like a large score to motivate them?
And before this move play, let's quickly slide these other variables bad and then move our score to
great to the top much more.
And also we it will just double click on it displays as one very large number.
Well, with all that done, we now have increasing difficulty, a score, and most importantly, super
robust code that allows us to adjust values in all our spaces easily.
So now for the absolute most important part, go and keep on playing the game until you reach a high
enough score that you can brag about.
So well done, you are really doing great!